Finding Aid for Historical Center for the Health Sciences (University of Michigan) records, 1831-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Historical Center for the Health Sciences (University of Michigan) records 1831-1992
University of Michigan. Historical Center for the Health Sciences.
93842 Bimu C502 2 UBImum C502
University of Michigan unit established in 1990 in part to collect and disseminate information regarding the history of health sciences in Michigan. Records include newsletter of the Center; collected historical manuscripts, photographs, and motion pictures relating to the development of health sciences at the University of Michigan; include notebooks of medical school students, account book, 1831-1839, of Berrien Springs, Michigan physician, and miscellaneous materials relating to the medical school and to medical practice.
0.6 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
3 film reels
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Historical Center for Health Sciences (Donor No. 8111 ) in November 1992.
The record group is open for research.
The Historical Center for the Health Sciences (HCHS) was founded in January 1990 at the University of Michigan for the purpose of "fostering broader understanding and deeper appreciation of the pioneering role taken by the University and the State of Michigan to advance knowledge of disease and promote human health" (Retrospectives, Spring 1992).
Through the efforts of Director Nicholas Steneck, HCHS has begun a ten-year campaign to establish a major program to serve the university and the state of Michigan by collecting and disseminating information regarding the history of health sciences in Michigan via lectures and conferences, and the publication of research guides, monographs, and its newsletter Retrospectives.
For more information regarding the activities and publications of HCHS, the researcher should consult the inaugural issue of Retrospectives (Spring 1992) located in Box 1 of the collection.
The records of the Historical Center for Health Sciences (HCHS) measure .6 linear feet. The records include a small file of administrative records documenting operation of the center and archival material collected by the center. The materials have been divided into two subgroups: Administrative and Collections.
Subjects:
Berrien Springs (Mich.); Medicine.; Physicians--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Historical Center for the Health Sciences.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan--Students--Manuscripts.; Medical sciences--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Hearts.; Medicine.; Surgery.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Historical Center for the Health Sciences.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
Genre Terms:
College publications.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Administrative
  The first subgroup, Administrative, consists of one series, Printed Materials. The Printed Materials series consists of HCHS's newsletter Retrospectives, first issued in Spring 1992.
  - Printed Materials
    - Newsletters
      - Retrospectives, 1992- (Box 1)
- Collections
  The second subgroup, Collections, consists of materials gathered together from a variety of sources by HCHS. These materials have been divided into three series reflecting the format of the records: Manuscripts, Photographs, and Films.
  Within each series in the Collections subgroup, the materials are arranged by Survey Numbers assigned by HCHS to control information in its database. A printout of these database records, also arranged by Survey Number, is attached to the end of the contents list. The researcher should consult the printout of database records for a more detailed description of each item and information regarding an item's acquisition by HCHS.
  Each of the folders contains the item(s) listed in the boxlist as well as any correspondence (generally between the donor and HCHS Director Nicholas Steneck) generated regarding the item(s).
  - Manuscripts
    The Manuscripts series contains a variety of material, including student notebooks from the late nineteenth century and early twentieth century and correspondence regarding medical issues. The account book of Dr. Samuel Castle Bartholomew, of Berrien Springs, Michigan, contains notes regarding his housecalls to patients in addition to financial information.
    - Student Notes and Materials (UM) of Horace Arthur Macy circa 1888, 91-001 (Box 1)
    - Letter to Senator W. R. Taylor from N. M. McCollum (urging a vote against House Bill No. 139) February 28, 1915, 91-002 (Box 1)
    - Invoice for Anatomical Supplies 1873, 91-010 (Box 1)
    - Student Notes (UM) of E. L. Hicks 1917, 92-001 (Box 1)
    - Medical Receipts and Records of Frank J. Kukla (University Hospital) 1935-1943, 92-004 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence from Dr. Edward S. Dunster (of UM) to Dr. William Goodell (Philadelphia) 1876, 1878 (photocopies), 92-007 (Box 1)
    - Speeches and Writings of Dr. Horace W. Davenport (of UM Physiology Department) 1970, 1976 undated, 92-008 (Box 1)
    - Student Notebook (UM) of F. A. Hargrave 1882, 92-026 (Box 1)
    - Account book of Dr. Samuel Castle Bartholomew (of Berrien Springs, Michigan) 1831-1839, 92-027 (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook, History of the University of Michigan Medical School Glee Club 1964-1969, 92-029 (Volume 1)
    - Commencements and Convocations at the UM Medical School (miscellaneous materials) 1959, 1961, 1968, 1969, 92-030 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    The series of Photographs consists primarily of photographs of early Medical School faculty. Also included are photographs of the Peterson Hospital and of the Phi Chi house (UM medical fraternity). The Peterson Hospital was founded by Dr. Reuben Peterson of UM in 1902 and was renamed the Ann Arbor Private Hospital in 1917.
    - Peterson Hospital and Staff circa 1908, 90-001 (Box 1)
    - Faculty and Staff, UM Medical School undated, 92-002 (Box 1)
      - Angell, James Burrill
      - Balmer, A.B.
      - Dunster, Edward S.
      - Ford, Corydon L.
      - Frothingham, George E.
      - Herdman, William J.
      - Langley, John N.
      - Maclean, Donald
      - Negley, ? (Janitor)
    - Phi Chi House (UM Medical Fraternity) undated, 92-003 (Box 1)
    - Faculty, UM Medical School undated, 93-001 (Box 1)
      - Vaughan, Victor Clarence [1]
      - Huber, G. Carl [2]
      - McCotter, Rollo E. [3]
      - Guild, Stacey R. [4]
      - Lombard, Warren Plimpton [5]
      - Novy, Frederick G. [6]
      - Edmunds, Charles W. [7]
      - Warthin, Aldred Scott [8]
      - Weller, Carl Vernon [9]
      - Peet, Max [10]
      - Wile, Udo J. [11]
      - Peterson, Reuben [12]
      - Cabot, Hugh [13]
  - Films
    The three films comprising the Films series date from the 1950s and 1970s and portray UM doctors performing various types of surgery.
    - Human Heart Transplantation performed by Drs. Donald K. Kahn and Herbert E. Sloan circa 1950s, 92-011; color; approx. 15 minutes; 16 mm; silent (Reel 1)
    - Intestinal Surgery performed by Dr. William Fry February 1, 1972, 92-013; color; approx. 12 minutes; 16 mm; silent (Reel 2)
    - Surgery performed by Dr. Child May 5, 1971, 92-014; color; approx. 20 minutes; 16 mm; silent (Reel 3)